ILGWU Southeast Region Audio Recordings 5780/058 AV
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
ILGWU Southeast Region Audio Recordings
1975-1979
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union
5780/058 AV
1 cubic feet
1 linear ft.
Audiovisual materials.
This collection contains audio recordings of the Southeast Region's conferences in 1978 and 1979, as well as audio recordings of speeches and Union Label songs.
7128698
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
D. Mordente, December 02, 2008
EAD encoding:
Kheel Staff, April 10, 2019
Biographical / Historical
The International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union was once one of the largest labor unions in the United States founded in 1900 by local union delegates representing about 2,000 members in cities in the northeastern United States. It was one of the first U.S. Unions to have a membership consisting of mostly females, and it played a key role in the labor history of the 1920s and 1930s. The union is generally referred to as the "ILGWU" or the "ILG". The ILGWU grew in geographical scope, membership size, and political influence to become one of the most powerful forces in American organized labor by mid-century. Representing workers in the women's garment industry, the ILGWU worked to improve working and living conditions of its members through collective bargaining agreements, training programs, health care facilities, cooperative housing, educational opportunities, and other efforts. The ILGWU merged with the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union in 1995 to form the Union of Needle trades, Industrial and Textile Employees (UNITE). UNITE merged with the Hotel Employees and Restaurant Employees Union (HERE) in 2004 to create a new union known as UNITE HERE. The two unions that formed UNITE in 1995 represented only 250,000 workers between them, down from the ILGWU's peak membership of 450,000 in 1969.
Biographical / Historical
Established in 1937, the Southeast Region of the ILGWU covered eight states: Alabama, Florida, Georgia, Louisiana, Mississippi, North Carolina, South Carolina, and Tennessee.
John S. Martin served as director from the regional department's founding until his retirement in 1954. Elmer Kehrer succeeded him, holding the position until resignation in 1964. Martin Morand was director from 1964 to 1969, and after Morand's resignation, Nicholas Bonanno was appointed Director of the Southeast Region. Bonnano was still director of the region, at the time of the ILGWU's merger with ACTWU in 1995.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of reel to reel audio recordings, mainly of the Southeast Region Conference for various years, but there is also material on the union label song, as well as director's speeches.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 5780: ILGWU records 5780/058: ILGWU Southeast Region Records
Women's clothing industry -- United States; Labor unions -- Clothing workers -- United States; Clothing workers -- United States; Industrial relations -- United States; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union. -- Southeast Region.
7128698
- Union Strike, 1975; 1 (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents
  August 7, 1975 meeting, 215-229; marking on front: 9/6/74: reel #1, side #1 first session; 9/7/74: reel #2, side #2 morning session
- First Morning, Director, State Directors, 1975; 2 (Box 1)
  August 7, 1975
- Nashville, 1975; 3 (Box 1)
  1 7/8 speed
- ILGWU Union Label Songs., 1976; 4 (Box 1)
- Birmingham. Director's Speech on Israel Visit., 1976; 5 (Box 1)
- Southeast Region Conference., 1978; 6 (Box 1)
  August 4, 1978; Dan Miller, President, Florida American Federation of Labor; Evelyn Dubrow, V.P.; Lou Rolnick; Bob Cheponis; Q &A Lucie Roberts (516), Shirley Cook (384); James Gutmann; Q & A Betty (523, New Bern, N.C. Health (?), Adel Lacy; Fred Siems
- Southeast Region Conference. Atlanta., 1978; 7 (Box 1)
  August, 4, 1978; Singing; Berger; Busky (?); Berger; Bonanno; Dan Savage (Alabama); Art Martin (North Carolina); Lennie Finkel (Florida); Mike Ruano (?) (Florida); Mary Cameron (Tennessee); Joe Ferguson (South Carolina)
- Southeast Region Conference., 1978; 8 (Box 1)
  August, 5, 1978; 2nd Day, Atlanta Regency. Opening Singing, Approx. 44; Bonanno (Introduction), 65; Chaikin, 370; Bonanno; Berger, 630, end Georgia report, Benefit Fund; Bruce Barcan (?); Dorothy Armstrong, 576K; Eunice Snyder, 467; Mildred Bennett, 480; Edna Smith, 308, Adel Lay, 555; Shuan Ratcliff, 305C; 3, Rosalie Tucker, 581; 9, Shirley Jones, 363; 11 Betty Davis, 576Q; Jane Rutledge (?), 408, 566; Emma King, 417; Aileen Brown, 515
- Southeast Region Conference. Atlanta 2nd Day., 1978; 9 (Box 1)
  Afternoon session. Nick Bonanno; Cecil Brandstetter, Attorney; Erving Gordon; Nick Zeigler
- Southeast Region Conference. Atlanta. Afternoon Session., 1978; 10 (Box 1)
  Banquet
- Southeast Region Conference. [tape 1], 1979; 11 (Box 1)
- Southeast Region Conference. [tape 2], 1979; 12 (Box 1)
- Southeast Region Conference. [tape 3], 1979; 13 (Box 1)
- Audio digitized from the collection. (Box 2)